http://youtu.be/ndvwEznOyCc
http://youtu.be/ndvwEznOyCc
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: In this short video,
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: trong video ngắn này,
we'd like to look up the data sheet to learn
ta sẽ đọc data sheet để học
about the memory layout on the microcontroller.
về sắp xếp bộ nhớ của vi điều khiển.
So let's go to the table of contents.
Nhìn vào mục lục.
And we'll look up the overview of the microcontroller, which is 1.2.
Ta thấy tổng quan của vi điều khiển , là phần 1.2.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Click right here.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: click vào đó.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yeah.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Đúng rồi.
So we notice that these have been checked.
Ta nhớ là ta coi phần này rồi.
What we looking for is how much flash memory it has.
Thứ mà ta tìm là bộ nhớ flash có dung lượng bao nhiêu.
And how much system RAM it has.
bộ nhớ RAM có dung lượng bao nhiêu.
The flash memory is where our code is going to go.
Bộ nhớ flash là nơi ta sẽ chứa code.
So we know that we have a capacity of 256 kilobytes.
ta có khoảng 256 kilobytes.
And our data is going to go in the RAM, which is a limit of 32 kilobytes.
RAM sẽ chứa dữ liệu, có giới hạn là 32 kilobytes.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right, so the next question we might want to ask
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: được rồi, câu hỏi kế tiếp là
is, where or what addresses are our memory?
đâu là địa chỉ của bộ nhớ này?
So we go back to the table of contents and look for more things on memory.
cho nên, ta quay lại mục lục và tìm thêm thông tin về bộ nhớ.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So go to Section 2.4.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: vậy hãy tới phần 2.4.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Right there.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Nó đó.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And that tells you our memory model.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: nó sẽ nói cho bạn mô hình của bộ nhớ.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Here is our memory model.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: đây là mô hình bộ nhớ của chúng ta.
We can see that we have 256 kilobytes of ROM located at these addresses.
Ta thấy 256 kilobytes ROM được xếp ở những địa chỉ này.
And we have 32 kilobytes of RAM located at those addresses.
Và 32 kilobytes RAM được xếp ở đằng kia.
Also in this data sheet, it tells us what we use the memory for.
và trong data sheet này, nó cũng sẽ nói cho biết ta xài bộ nhớ để làm gì.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So this table, table 2.5,
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: như bảng 2.5 này,
tells us that we use the memory region here for Code.
nói cho ta biết dùng phân vùng bộ nhớ này cho code.
This region from 0x2000.0000 onwards is used for data.
Phân vùng từ 0x2000.0000 trở lên sẽ dùng cho dữ liệu.
And then we have our device IO registers, which are here.
và ta có những thanh ghi IO cho thiết bị ngoại vi ở đây.
These are all our GPIO pins.
Đây là cho những chân GPIO.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: But Ramesh, is that all the registers?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Khoan đã Ramesh, đây có phải là tất cả thanh ghi?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: There's some extra registers.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: có thêm vài thanh ghi khác nữa.
These are our Private Peripheral Bus.
Đây là Bus thiết bị ngoại vi của chúng ta.
These are devices like our NVIC and our SYSTICK.
Những thiết bị như là NVIC và SYSTICK.
These are right here.
sẽ ở đây.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Được rồi.
So again, use the data sheet to look things up.
1 lần nữa, xài data sheet để tìm thông tin.
Don't be afraid to search around.
Đừng sợ phải kiếm vòng vòng.
There's a lot of information in there.
Có rất nhiều thông tin ở đây.